{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>One rearguard action after this battle was defeated at the Battle of Kip\u2019s Landing, though John Glover\u2019s Marblehead fishermen provided a more successful rearguard at Pell\u2019s Point. General Alexander Stirling was captured at this battle, where the Gowanus Heights</b> <b>were fortified by (+)</b> <b>Israel Putnam but the Jamaica Road was left unguarded. That road</b> <b>was used by Henry Clinton to outflank the American defenders, although he let them escape after declining to attack (*)</b> Brooklyn Heights. For the point, name this August 1776 Revolutionary War battle, after which George Washington lost control of New York.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Long Island</b> (accept Battle of<b> Brooklyn</b> Heights before \u201cBrooklyn Heights\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this event, a character foreshadows that \u201cstony limits cannot hold love out.\u201d The modern setting for this event was foreign to the author; instead, this scene\u2019s modern staging was introduced by Thomas Otway\u2019s highly-imitative</b><em><b> History and Fall of Caius Marius</b></em><b>,</b> <b>during which (+)</b> <b>Lavinia says \u201cbe but sworn my Love / and I\u2019ll no longer call Metellus</b> <b>Lavinia says \u201cbe but sworn my Love / and I\u2019ll no longer call Metellus</b> <b>parent.\u201d The line \u201cBut (*)</b> <b>parent.\u201d The line \u201cBut (*)</b> soft! What light through yonder window breaks?\u201d opens, for the point, what scene that traditionally takes place in and above the Capulets\u2019 garden in Shakespeare\u2019s<em> Romeo and</em> <em>Juliet</em>?", "answer": "Romeo and Juliet\u2019s<b> balcony</b> scene (accept<b> Act 2, Scene 2</b> of Romeo and Juliet)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this Mexican revolutionary leader who ousted Victoriano Huerta and gained power over Mexico, becoming its first President under the Constitution of 1917.", "answer": "Jos\u00b4e Venustiano<b> Carranza</b> Garza", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. For their participation in this activity, husband-and-wife team Serge and Beate Klarsfeld were targeted by an unsuccessful car bombing in 1979. The</b> <b>ODESSA network set up numerous (+)</b> <b>\u201cratlines\u201d to help targets of this activity escape.</b> <b>This activity was successfully undertaken on Garibaldi Avenue in (*)</b> Buenos Aires on May 11, 1960, and was pursued by Simon Wiesenthal. For the point, name this activity, carried out by Mossad, to find and bring people like Adolf Eichmann to trial.", "answer": "<b> hunt</b>ing (or<b> search</b>ing, etc.) for ex-<b>Nazi</b>s (accept anything that mentions attempting to capture ex-<b>Nazi</b>s; between the mentions of Simon Wiesenthal and Adolf Eichmann, accept<b> capturing </b>Adolf<b> Eichmann</b> specifically)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This city was divided into districts dedicated to Anu and the goddess Inanna, the latter of whom is depicted in the Mask of Warka found at this city. In a regional King List, this city earned its fifth listed dynasty under Utu-hengal, though Ur-Namma quickly brought its rival back to power. (+) Enmerkar is credited with founding this city on what was then the banks of the Euphrates, which fueled a system of canals within this (*) </b> Sumerian city. This city\u2019s walls were legendarily built by a man who was one-third mortal. For the point, name this Sumerian city legendarily ruled by Gilgamesh.", "answer": "<b> Uruk</b> (accept<b> Erech</b> or<b> Eresh</b>; accept<b> Unug</b>-Kulaba; do not accept or prompt on Ur)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This monarch successfully pushed for abolishing the Remplacement system for military conscription. This monarch married his mistress Caroline Lacroix five days before his death,</b> <b>and survived an assassination attempt by Genaro (+)</b> <b>Rubio. Mark Twain criticized this</b> <b>man\u2019s policies in a soliloquy named after him. This man formed the Force Publique to enforce his rule in a certain area, but was criticized in the (*)</b> Casement Report, which detailed atrocities inflicted upon rubber harvesters. For the point, name this Belgian monarch best known for his exploitation of the Congo Free State.", "answer": "King<b> Leopold II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>One of these people is told \u201cFirst prize often goes to rank beginners\u201d by the Proprietor, who hands him an \u201cIvor Johnson...32...rubber handle.\u201d In a duet, two of these people beg \u201cLet me prove worthy of your love\u201d to the unseen Charlie and Jodie. The song (+)\u201cEverybody\u2019s Got the Right\u201d opens the musical in which these people appear; in a reprise of that song, these people (*)</b> open fire on the audience. For the point, name these people, the title figures of a Stephen Sondheim musical whose numbers include \u201cThe Gun Song\u201d and \u201cNovember 22, 1963.\u201d", "answer": "Presidential<b> Assassin</b>s (accept descriptions and equivalents)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A highly effective ambulance corps was implemented during this war by the Letterman system. It didn\u2019t involve France, but women called vivandieres assisted troops during this war. Richard Kirkland\u2019s assistance to the wounded at a battle in this war earned him the nickname \u201cThe Angel of (+) Marye\u2019s Height.\u201d The Christian Commission and the Sanitary Commission were founded during this war. Nurses who served during this war included (*) </b>Dorothea Dix and a woman who founded the American Red Cross. For the point, name this war in which Clara Barton served as a nurse at battles like Fredericksburg.", "answer": "American<b> Civil</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man tried to destroy his second symphony, written to celebrate American fighter pilots in World War II. He expressed longing for his Mount Kisco home in the neoclassical </b><em><b>Capricorn Concerto</b></em><b>. A prose poem by James Agee provided the text of his</b><em><b> Knoxville:</b></em> <em><b>Summer of 1915</b></em><b>. Another piece by this partner of (+)</b> <b>Gian Carlo Menotti was arranged</b> <b>from the second movement of his string quartet and was played on air to mourn the (*) </b>deaths of Franklin Roosevelt and John F. Kennedy. For the point, name this American composer of the <em>Adagio for Strings</em>.", "answer": "Samuel<b> Barber</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "For the point, name this feat, first accomplished by Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary.", "answer": "<b> climbing</b> (or<b> ascending</b>) Mount<b> Everest</b> (accept<b> Sagarmatha</b> or<b> Chomolungma</b> for Everest)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler built a series of forts called the Ripa Sarmatica along the Danube for a man who defeated the Persians at the Battle of Satala. This ruler rose to his highest position</b> <b>after Carus was struck by (+)</b> <b>lightning. This ruler created a system that was officially</b> <b>ended by Constantine the Great\u2019s \u201cprinciple of succession\u201d and failed to curb inflation with his Edict of (*) </b> Maximum Prices. For the point, name this Roman Emperor who ruled alongside Galerius after establishing the Tetrarchy and embarked on the last major persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b> Diocletian</b> (or Gaius Aurelius Valerius<b> Diocletian</b>us Augustus)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The head of this leader\u2019s intelligence agency was caught giving bribes to various news channels in the Vladi-videos. Operation Chavin de Huantar was launched by this leader to end an Embassy hostage crisis. This leader\u2019s death squad attacked a barbecue party, believing it to be a Marxist gathering, in the Barrios Altos massacre. This leader of the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Grupo Colina death squad won the \u201cInternal conflict\u201d against the Tupac Amaru</b> <b>Grupo Colina death squad won the \u201cInternal conflict\u201d against the Tupac Amaru</b> <b>Revolutionary Movement and the (*)</b> <b>Revolutionary Movement and the (*)</b> Shining Path Guerillas. For the point, name this former President of Peru who was ousted on corruption charges in 2000, after which he fled to Japan.", "answer": "Alberto<b> Fujimori</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In medieval legend, this man used a large chunk of beef to torment two hungry griffins that he used to fly to heaven. Orientalist scholar Theodor N\u00a8oldeke identified this real-life person with the \u201ctwo-horned\u201d Quranic figure Dhul-Qarnayn. Medievals depicted this member of the (+) Nine Worthies in many namesake \u201cromances,\u201d which drew loosely on the historian Arrian. In real life, the snake-handler Olympias gave birth to this man, who declared himself to be the son of (*) </b> Zeus-Ammon while in Egypt. For the point, name this conqueror-king whose army marched to India from Macedon.", "answer": "<b> Alexander the Great</b> (or<b> Alexander III of Macedon</b>ia)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Hendrik Verwoerd responded to this leader by saying that there must \u201calso be justice to the white man.\u201d This leader, who claimed his country \u201chas never had it so good,\u201d was scandalized after it was uncovered that Christine Keeler was in a relationship with Secretary</b> <b>of State for War John (+)</b> <b>Profumo. This leader declared that decolonization is inevitable</b> <b>Profumo. This leader declared that decolonization is inevitable</b> <b>in a speech given in Cape Town that observed the title phenomenon (*)</b> <b>in a speech given in Cape Town that observed the title phenomenon (*)</b> \u201cblowing through\u201d Africa. For the point, name this Conservative Prime Minister of Great Britain who gave the \u201cWind of Change\u201d speech.", "answer": "Harold<b> MacMillan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Baldur von Schirach and Artur Axmann were leaders of this organization. Members of this organization made up the majority of Kurt \u201cPanzer\u201d Meyer\u2019s 12th SS Panzer Division. Despite nominally being part of it, Hans Scholl, a member of the White (+) Rose, opposed this organization\u2019s beliefs. Members of this organization served as \u201cflak helpers\u201d manning antiaircraft guns, and many were recruited into the (*)</b> Volksturm alongside veterans of previous wars at the end of World War II. The Bund Deutscher M\u00a8adel was a branch of this organization that enrolled girls. For the point, name this organization for young people in Nazi Germany.", "answer": "<b> Hitler Youth</b> (prompt on Bund Deutscher M\u00a8adel before mentioned; prompt on Deutsches Jungvolk, prompt on Nazi Party)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A Presbyterian example of these figures travels with Ralpho and is the namesake of Samuel Butler\u2019s poem \u201cHudibras.\u201d One of these figures loses his wits, after which another</b> <b>named Astolfo travels to the (+)</b> <b>moon to find them. That first example of these figures</b> <b>moon to find them. That first example of these figures</b> <b>loves the pagan Angelica and kills King (*)</b> <b>loves the pagan Angelica and kills King (*)</b> Agramante, and is based on one of these who blows his oliphant horn before dying in an ambush in the Pyrenees. For the point, name these medieval figures, such as Roland and the warriors of the Round Table.", "answer": "<b> knight</b>s (accept<b> paladin</b>s; prompt on soldiers, crusaders, cavaliers, etc.; prompt on Parliamentarians or Roundheads before \u201cpagan\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>A French Mirage 2000 jet was shot down by forces carrying out this event near the town of Pale. The \u201cRomeo and Juliet\u201d of this event\u2019s location were killed while trying to cross the Vrbanja [vir-bahn-ya] Bridge, which was part of Sniper Alley. Mortar shell attacks on the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Markale Marketplace during this event were used to justify the NATO-led Operation</b> <b>Deliberate Force. This event ended shortly after the signing of the Dayton Agreement, which ended a conflict where the Republic of (*)</b> Srpska tried to unify with Serbia. For the point, name this almost 4-year-long siege of a capital city during the Bosnian War.", "answer": "Siege of<b> Sarajevo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This leader initially gave support to Plinio Salgado\u2019s Integralists in order to suppress communism in his country. \u201cThe Black Angel\u201d was the head of this leader\u2019s bodyguards,</b> <b>who plotted an assassination attempt against journalist Carlos (+)</b> <b>Lacerda; that scandal</b> <b>led this leader to write the Letter of Testament shortly before committing suicide. The rise to power of this \u201cFather of the Poor\u201d led to the end of his country\u2019s (*)</b> \u201ccoffee and milk\u201dpolitics. A South American Estado Novo was established by, for the point, what President of Brazil during the 1930s?", "answer": "Getulio<b> Vargas</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1957, the man holding this position was demoted to head of the Economics Institute after he joined one of his predecessors in the failed Anti-Party Group plot. After another man in this post lied about airlifting food, he had his name appended to the RRAB-3 (+) </b> <b>bomb dispenser. This position was held for over 28 years by Andrei Gromyko and for 10 years by a man who signed a 1939 agreement with German (*) </b> counterpart Joachim von Ribbentrop. For the point, name this position held during World War II by Vyacheslav Molotov, in which capacity he signed a non-aggression pact with Germany.", "answer": "<b> Minister</b> of<b> Foreign</b> Affairs of the<b> Soviet</b> Union (or<b> Narkomindel</b>; or People\u2019s Commissar for<b> Foreign</b> Affairs of the<b> Soviet</b> Union; or Minister of<b> External</b> Relations of the<b> Soviet</b> Union; accept <b>U</b>nion of<b> S</b>oviet<b> S</b>ocialist <b>R</b>epublics for \u201cSoviet Union\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The Japanese cruise ship</b><em><b> Haguro</b></em><b> was sunk in this body of water, which shares its name with a sultanate founded by Parameswara. The state of Negeri Sembilan has a coastline on this body of water, just a few miles southeast of a city in the Klang Valley where the (+) Petronas Towers were built. The significance of this body of water to international trade would be reduced by a canal through the Isthmus of (*)</b> Kra, as proposed by Thailand. For the point, name this strait that separates the Malay Peninsula from the island of Sumatra.", "answer": "Strait of<b> Malacca</b> (or<b> Malacca</b> Strait)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Margaret Thatcher\u2019s son Mark was imprisoned after supporting a 2004 coup attempt in this country. Prisoners in this country were executed to the tune of the song \u201cThose Were</b> <b>the Days\u201d by a firing squad dressed up as (+)</b> <b>Santa Claus. This country, which gained</b> <b>independence under Francisco Macias Nguema, is currently led by his nephew, Teodoro Obiang. Oil reserves off of (*)</b> Bioko Island heavily bolster the GDP, if not the general welfare of, for the point, what former Spanish colony in Sub-Saharan Africa whose capital is Malabo?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Equatorial Guinea</b> (do not accept or prompt on Guinea)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Ed Macauley and Cliff Hagan were traded to St. Louis for this player during a draft that provided this player with teammates K.C. Jones and Tommy Heinsohn. The Finals (+) MVP award is now named for this man; it was first awarded in 1969 to Jerry West, whose Lakers (*)</b> lost to this player-coach\u2019s team for the sixth time in a decade. For the point, name this first African-American coach in the NBA, a rival of Wilt Chamberlain and 11-time NBA champion center for the Boston Celtics.", "answer": "William Felton \u201cBill\u201d<b> Russell</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>Daniel Horsmanden led trials after this colony\u2019s supposed Negro Insurrection of 1741. Timothy Ruggles chaired an organization in this colony that passed the Declaration of Rights and Grievances protesting the 1765 Stamp Act. Governor Francis (+) Nicholson fled this colony due to a rebellion led by Jacob Leisler. Prior to becoming an English colony, it was led by Peter (*)</b> Stuyvesant, who oversaw the building of Broad Street in its largest city. For the point, name this American colony whose largest city served as national capital under the Constitution, preceding Philadelphia and Washington, D.C.", "answer": "Province of<b> New York</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The \u201cArm of the Arab Revolution\u201d led by Carlos the Jackal held hostages in this city. Gabriel D\u2019Annunzio dropped thousands of propaganda leaflets over this city during a \u201cflight over\u201d it. A film set in this city included (+) zither music by Anton Karas and a screenplay by Graham Greene; that film,</b><em><b> The Third Man</b></em><b>, was set during its Allied occupation. The (*) </b>Kahlenberg hill lies within this city, where King Jan Sobieski of Poland repelled Ottoman forces in 1683. For the point, name this former resident city of the Habsburgs and capital city of Austria.", "answer": "<b> Vienna</b> (or<b> Wien</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Both William S. Clark and Horace Capron developed the agriculture and industry of this island. Pavel Lebedev-Lastochkin sent a trade mission to this island, where he met the Matsumae. Shakushain revolted on this island, which was the center of a government</b> <b>supported by (+)</b> <b>Jules Brunet and based on American democracy. That government, led</b> <b>Jules Brunet and based on American democracy. That government, led</b> <b>by Enomoto Takeaki, was ousted after the Battle of (*)</b> <b>by Enomoto Takeaki, was ousted after the Battle of (*)</b> Hakodate after being formed by the shogun who had lost the Boshin War. The Republic of Ezo was based on, for the point, what island home of the Ainu, the northernmost of Japan\u2019s four main islands?", "answer": "<b> Hokkaido</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This pathogen\u2019s most recent pandemic is caused by its El Tor biotype. This bacterium\u2019s namesake toxin activates constitutive cyclic AMP production and causes dumping of</b> <b>water into the intestinal lumen. The UN invoked diplomatic immunity after (+)</b> <b>Nepalese</b> <b>peacekeepers were accused of spreading this pathogen. One outbreak of this disease was traced back to the Broad Street (*) </b> pump using a dot map by John Snow, and the most recent epidemic of this disease followed a 2010 earthquake. For the point, name this disease that causes rice water diarrhea and is still ravaging Haiti.", "answer": "<b> cholera</b> (accept<b> V</b>ibrio<b> cholerae</b>, do not accept or prompt on dysentery)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "<b>A speech given in support of this agreement claimed that \u201cthe gains from this agreement will be your gains too.\u201d The passage of this agreement led to a surge in the number of cheap-labor factories called (+)</b><em><b> maquiladoras</b></em><b>. Ross Perot made opposing the ratification of this agreement a central pillar in his platform for his 1992 presidential campaign, claiming that it would make a \u201cgiant sucking sound going (*) </b> south.\u201d The Zapatista movement declared open rebellion against a signatory of, for the point, what 1994 agreement that dramatically lowered or eliminated tariffs between Canada, Mexico, and the United States?", "answer": "<b> N</b>orth<b> A</b>merican<b> F</b>ree<b> T</b>rade<b> A</b>greement", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}